Jacopo Biscella

Software Engineering Team Leader

jacopo@biscella.com • +44 743 463 6284 • https://www.linkedin.com/in/jacopobiscella/

Summary

I've supported teams to successfully deliver complex projects by aligning innovation with business goals. My participative leadership creates efficient, high-performing environments.

My guidance at Global Relay was instrumental in developing a microservice infrastructure, aiming at a significant monthly revenue recovery of \$850,000.

Often recognized for the ability to rapidly integrate into new teams and drive improvements. Increased team velocity by up to 40% through agile methodologies at both Global Relay and Ocado.

My experience is further enriched by a strong foundation in architectural design, optimizing processes and advocating for a culture of mentoring, transparency, and ongoing learning.

Skills

Soft Skills:

- Leadership Skills: I encourage team building through open communication and constructive conflict resolution. I also mentor team members and foster their professional development.
- ▼ Interpersonal Skills: I believe in empathizing with colleagues to facilitate collaboration across functions. I also make an effort to avoid unnecessary conflicts.
- Strategic Project Management: I carefully consider risks and how to most responsibly delegate tasks for optimal team performance.
- Agile methodologies: I have applied values and practices from Scrum, Kanban, TDD, BDD and Lean methodologies over the years, always trying to find the best balance for the context over applying principles by the book.

Technical Skills:

- Programming languages: Java, Bash; minor experiences in Scala, TypeScript and Python.
- Frameworks and Technologies: Spring Boot, Apache Kafka, CockroachDB, REST, Eclipse Vert.x, jUnit, Cucumber, Selenium WebDriver, Robot Framework, jBoss javassist.
- Tools and Platforms: Jenkins, Docker, Kubernetes, OpenShift, Git, BitBucket, Jira, Confluence.

Professional Experience

Global Relay, London, UK: Global Relay provides fully compliant cloud-based archiving, monitoring and discovery solutions to 22 of the top 25 global banks and over 20,000 customers across 90+ countries.

As Software Engineering Team Leader at Global Relay

Feb 2023 - current

- **T** Led a cross functional team of eight developers in implementing an event based microservice infrastructure for billing reconciliation with the target of recovering up to 850.000\$ per month of missing revenue.
- **Toached** the team in **improving velocity by 40%** and guaranteeing **non regression of features** by coaching the members to adopt agile methodologies such **SCRUM**, **BDD** and **TDD**.
- Mentored senior team members, fostering technical ownership, and mentorship skills.
- Actively participated in the interview process, contributing to the selection of high-quality engineers.
- **Established and monitored performance goals** for team members.
- Translated raw requirements into actionable backlog items.
- Contributed to **architectural studies**, influencing sprint-focused increments.
- Tech Stack: based on Java, CockroachDB, Apache Kafka, jUnit, Mockito, Cucumber, Docker, Jenkins, Git, Kubernetes.

As Senior Software Engineer at Global Relay

Jan 2022 - Feb 2023

- Enhanced architectural solutions by integrating Global Relay Message with the meta business portal.
- Developed a distributed state machine for data reconciliation to ensure archival compliance.
- Led memory investigation efforts, performed application profiling, and provided mentorship to team members.
- Tech Stack: based on Java, jUnit, Mockito, Aerospike, Eclipse Vert.X, RX Java, Cucumber, Docker, Jenkins, Git, Kubernetes.

Ocado Technology, London, UK: Ocado Technology designs and builds solutions including cloud orchestration systems for automated robotic warehouses, grocery ecommerce platforms and logistics. They provide proprietary technologies for Ocado and third party retailers like Kroger in the US.

As Senior Software Engineer at Ocado Technology

Oct 2020 - Jan 2022

- **T** Led the **migration** of the legacy system for cloud orchestration of the decant into robotic warehouses to a **microservice architecture**, covering the lifecycle from study to implementation planning.
- The streamlined the CI/CD process, reducing manual setup for new warehouses from over 2 weeks to less than an hour.
- **Studied** and developed microservices supporting robotic warehouses fulfillment.
- **Coached** the team in **adopting agile principles** to provide predictable metrics for upper management and sustainable task assignments.
- Organized educational sessions to enhance team members' understanding of architecture concepts in preparation for system redesign and migration to an AWS/Java platform.
- Tech Stack: based on Java, Scala, Akka, Mockito, Selenium Webdriver, Apache Cassandra, GitLab, Cucumber, Docker, Git, Kubernetes.

Amadeus, London, UK: Amadeus develops IT solutions powering air travel and tourism ecosystems globally, processing over 400 million transactions daily across airline partners and travel agencies.

As Senior Software Engineer and Scrum Master at Amadeus

Jul 2015 - Oct 2020

- Designed and implemented a lightweight AOP (Aspect-Oriented Programming) framework and utilized it to develop a tool to generate tests using live data.
- The Contributes both to architectural studies and implementations to build a real time microservice platfrom aimed at implementing a new system to allow customers to interact in real time with Amadeus data in an event based fashion.
- Led **Agile adoption** and served as Scrum Master for globally **distributed teams**, streamlining development processes.
- **Mentored** less experienced software engineers in various daily activities.
- Tech Stack: based on Java, Groovy, Apache Kafka, jUnit, mockito, Robot Framework, MongoDB, Git, QF Test, Java Swing, OpenShift, Docker, Kubernetes.

......

NetProphecy LTD, London, UK: Startup consultancy for small to medium-sized companies.

As Co Founder and Software Engineering Team Leader

Apr 2011 - Jul 2015

- Successfully managed several teams/projects for customers in the London and Milan areas using agile methodologies.
- f T Led **IT staff selection** and training both for NetProphecy and customers.
- Engineered and implemented various **custom business software**, in particular web based ERP/CRM solutions and mobile applications and related backends, by overseeing the **full lifecycle** of the projects.
- ♣ Tech Stack: based on Java, PHP, MySQL, jUnit, Mockito, Selenium Webdriver, Cucumber, MySQL, PostgreSQL, J2ME, Docker, Kubernetes.

Previous professional experiences (2002 - 2011)

Over the years, I've partnered with various companies and institutions, including the University of Milan and Mixel S.c.a.r.I., to develop cutting-edge mobile solutions. I've contributed to the development of a web-based ERP system utilizing ZK, jBoss AS, and MySQL, collaborated with AIMPES Servizi SRL on numerous IT projects, and engaged with the Italian public administration.

Education

Bachelor Degree in Digital Communication (Comunicazione Digitale), University of Milan

2004

Nationality and Languages

Nationality: Italian, British.

Languages: Italian (native), English (fluent).